let's look at the solution for our one
bit history quiz we have a one bit
history that starts at zero and two bit
counter for each possible history all
counterstart it's strong not taken and
the pattern we're trying to predict is
the not taken not taken taken etc after
100 repetitions of this pattern what is
the total number of mispredictions that
we will have seen one way to approach
this problem is simply to work through
the table like we have seen before so we
will have our state the prediction
the outcome
and whether we are correct
and now we will just work through the
outcomes the outcomes will be
n
t
t etc and of course we will not go
through 100 repetitions of this pretty
soon the predictor will start to be very
consistent about what it's predicting in
each round of the pattern the state
initially is zero strong not taken
strong not taken
the prediction as a result of that will
be
use the zeroth counter which is saying
strong not taken so the prediction will
be not taken
this agrees with the outcome so we are
correct
update the predictor
so the state will be zero because the
outcome was not taken strong not taken
will be updated with a not taken outcome
so it stays strong not taken and the
other counter just stays the same now
the predictor again will predict not
taken using zero and strong not taken
and it will again be correct so the
history stays at zero the strong note
taken stays at strong note taken and the
other counter just stays the same and at
this point we will again with a history
of zero use this predict not taken
strongly and be wrong this time so after
one round we have a single misprediction
the history will be
one now
and the predictor here
will be updated
to weak not taken because there has been
a taken outcome and the other predictor
just stays the same now we will use a
history of one
to index say strong not taken
so the outcome will be not taken and be
correct next
we will
keep the strong note taken here the
other counter stays the same
the history becomes zero because of this
and we will use
a history of zero to index into the weak
not taken state and thus predict not
taken again
again we are correct in our decision
next
the history stays zero because the
decision was not taken the update of the
weak knock taken goes back to the strong
not taken because the decision was not
taken the other counter stays the same
and using the history of zero we will
index and use this counter
this counter says truck not taken so we
will predict not taken this will
disagree with the taken prediction so we
will have a misprediction
this concludes round two as you can see
at the end of round two we have the same
state that we had at the end of round
one so now pretty much what happened in
round two will repeat more times
overall in the hundred repetitions of
this in each repetition we have a single
misprediction so the correct answer is
that we have a hundred mispredictions or
one third
of our decisions are wrong as you can
see the one bit history predictor is not
a great predictor for this type of a
pattern